In real life, events often depend on each other.
في الحياة الواقعية، تعتمد الأحداث في الغالب على بعضها البعض.
Say you can be an early bird or night owl.
لنفترض أن بإمكانك أن تكون طائر مبكر أو بومة ليلية.
And for the sake of simplicity,
وتوخيًا للبساطة،
let's assume there's a 50 percent chance for each one.
لنفترض أن هناك فرصة بنسبة 50٪ لكل احتمال منهم.
Now whether you decide to go for a run at 5:00 a.m. tomorrow is not entirely independent.
والآن إذا قررت الذهاب للجري في تمام الساعة 5:00. غدًا ليس منفصلًا بشكل تام.
I would argue that going for a run at 5:00 a.m. is not likely for most people.
ولكني أزعم أن الذهاب للجري في الساعة 5:00 صباحًا غير مرجح بالنسبة إلى معظم الأشخاص.
But it is certainly more likely for individuals who are actually awake at that hour.
ولكن من المؤكد أنه مرجح أكثر بالنسبة إلى الأفراد الذين يستيقظون بالفعل في تلك الساعة.
If you're an early bird,
إذا كنت طائر صباحي،
the probability might be a two percent chance,
فقد يكون الاحتمال فرصة بنسبة 2 في المائة،
while if you're a night owl,
أما إذا كنت بومة ليلية،
the probability might be zero.
فقد يكون الاحتمال صفر.
You can think of these events as two consecutive coin flips.
يمكنك أن تفكر في هذه الأحداث كقلب العملة المتتابع.
The first coin determines whether you're an early bird,
تحدد العملة الأولى ما إذا كنت طائر صباحي،
and the second coin is only flipped given that you are an early bird,
والعملة الثانية انقلبت فقط بالنظر إلى أنك طائر صباحي،
and it determines if you go for the run.
ويحدد ذلك إذا كنت قد ذهبت للجري.
We are no longer observing independent events,
لم نعد نراقب الأحداث المستقلة،
like we did in the last lesson,
ومثلما فعلنا في الدرس الأخير،
where the outcome of the first coin flip didn't affect the outcome of the second.
حيث لم تؤثر نتيجة أول عملة معدنية في نتائج العملة الثانية.
Starting with this lesson,
وبدءًا من هذا الدرس،
we're going to look at case studies where the outcome of the
سننظر في دراسات الحالة التي تؤثر فيها العملة الأولى
first does impact the outcome of the second.
في نتائج العملة الثانية.